               Regional Inequality in Australia 
                   Submission 19









Senate Enquiry into Inequality in Regional Australia






      Submission by Gal Sypher




       Gai Sypher, am pleased to make a submission to the inquiry into inequality in 
      regional Australia. This submission will address inequality relating to the provision of 
      age care in regional and remote Queensland. More broadly this submission will 
      focus on the lack of sustainability for the age care industry in regional and remote 
      regions based on the current business driven model.

      The region referred to in this report cover Central and Central Western Queensland.
























      RECOMMENDATION

      Work collaboratively to develop relevant models of care. It will be important for 
      service providers to collaborate to innovatively develop models of care that will 
      work in rural and remote areas and I advocate on behalf of aged people to the 
      Federal Government to consider this so that:

        • Services provision is available
        ■ financial and efficient services can be provided to clients
        ■ they receive equitable care and choices
        • the challenges they face are reduced, thereby relieving stress
        • transport issues are reduced
        • home service are available

                                      Regional Inequality in Australia 
                                               Submission 19


Submission - Senate Inquiry into inequality in Regional Australia 



Introduction

The aged care sector is one of Australia's largest and fastest growing service industries, employing 
over 350,000 people, with the Australian Government expected to spend $17.4 billion in 2016-17. 
The sector is currently in a phase of substantial transformation and growth. The majority of aged 
care services is supplied by not-for-profit service providers. The provision of aged care services — 
particularly residential places — can be costly, and private for-profit providers sometimes regard 
remote and regional areas as too expensive for them to operate profitably. With demand increasing 
as Australia's population ages, the Australian Government has introduced demand-driven service 
delivery that promotes Consumer Directed Care, to ensure the aged care system is sustainable.

Central and Central Western Queensland Region

In the Central and Central Western region of Queensland there are 72 different aged care services 
delivering aged care services. These provide 671 community care places; 1,643 residential aged care 
places, and 30 transition care places. For the year to June 2016, these services cost the Federal 
Government $111M.

The data below (Figure 25) shows that access to residential aged care in remote and very remote 
communities is extremely limited. The type of provider of residential aged care in rural and remote 
Australia differs from major cities substantially. The largest provider type in major cities is the 
private provider, but their market share outside major cities is extremely limited — particularly once 
you leave inner regional locations (National Rural Health Alliance Inc, 2016).




           Number of facilities by provider type by Remoteness Area
 100 

 700 

 600 

 500 
 400 

 300 

 200 

 100

          4Playrif 1.:11IC% esarr            Outer r capons'                      Ver-f rIntetceir
               Charstabi► ...Ir. C. °Mtn unity bassd M. Isopoar.    rm. air      C.Arverrunera




Private providers are not found in locations that operate on marginally sustainable business models, 
such as those facilities that operate in remote and very remote communities. The concept of 
consumer choice is thus more constrained as you progress into more remote locations. In these 
locations, the need for legislated requirements and regulation is vital to guarantee both access to 
residential and community based aged care and to an acceptable quality of care (National Rural 
Health Alliance Inc, 2016).

                 Regional Inequality in Australia
                    Submission 19




Problems faced by the elderly in regional and remote areas

Lack of choice

Aged care provision in rural and remote areas may be limited to one or two providers who have less 
need to compete for custom, through marketing or self-promotion, than their metropolitan 
counterparts, leading to 'information-poor' consumers. A small pool of providers may also result in 
lack of service differentiation or innovation (National Aged Care Alliance, 2017).

Issues engaging with My Aged Care

Older people living in rural and remote areas experience the same issues with My Aged Care, that 
have been identified in more populated areas, but their experience is exacerbated by the following:

  • poor or intermittent internet coverage
  • lack of access to computer equipment, especially Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander 
    people living in remote areas
  • lack of access to alternate sources of information
  • difficulties relating to distance, time and cost for services, including assessors' capacity to 
    provide face-to-face assessment in people's homes (National Aged Care Alliance, 2017). 

Issues highlighted by Aged & Community Services Australia

Aged & Community Services Australia CEO, Pat Sparrow, highlighted a number of issues that were 
particularly important for aged people in regional and remote regions:

  • The Government's current market approach to aged care will not work for regional, rural 
    and remote areas, so it is important to determine what will be viable (with regards to 
    funding) in these locations.
  • Rural properties cause difficulties when assessing assets, especially those that are the home 
    to two-three generations of family.
  • Transport costs for Home Care services do not change for clients that are in rural and 
    remote locations. It will be important for Government to look at how else to deliver services 
    to make services to people outside metropolitan areas practical and efficient.
  • It may be more efficient and practical for someone local (rural and remote) to be contracted 
    to help with support: e.g. household support, with other local community members carrying 
    out various tasks for efficiency.
  • Supported housing should be considered for a cheaper and better way to deliver home care
  • Need to consider the things that make rural and remote providers successful. 

What needs to happen in regional and remote areas

Work collaboratively to develop relevant models of care. It will be important for service providers 
to collaborate to innovatively develop models of care that will work in rural and remote areas and I 
advocate on behalf of aged people to the Federal Government to consider this so that:

  ▪ service provision is available
  • financial and efficient services can be provided to clients
  • they receive equitable care and choices where possible
  • the challenges they face are reduced, thereby relieving stress
  • transport issues are reduced
  • home services are available

