                      Regional Inequality in Australia 
                           Submission 26

jta UNIVERSITY OF                            DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
-4.4- CANBERRA




Senate Economics Reference Committee

Inquiry into the indicators of, and impact of, regional inequality in Australia 

Submission from the University of Canberra


The University of Canberra acknowledges the impact of regional inequality in Australia and welcomes the opportunity to 
provide a submission to this important Inquiry.

Noting the inquiry's letter and terms of reference, the University would like to inform the Committee of 'examples of 
solutions' that it provides in meeting the challenges of regional Australia, including reference to work with Aboriginal and 
Torres Strait Islander peoples.

The University of Canberra addresses regional inequality through outreach and widening participation, transformative 
education and mission-oriented problem-solving research.

University of Canberra
The University is incorporated under the University of Canberra Act 1989 of the Australian Capital Territory. 

It is committed to serving its communities through professional education and applied research.

It is committed to providing an exceptional student experience and world-ready graduates; excellence and innovation 
through integrated teaching, research and entrepreneurship; and to establishing a living-learning community that will enable 
residents to be immersed in the University's intellectual environment.

The University of Canberra is ranked in the top two percent of universities globally by both Times Higher Education (THE) and 
QS World University Rankings and appears in both the 2018 QS and the 2017 THE rankings as one of the top 100 universities 
under the age of 50 years.

The University of Canberra plays an important role in the community as staff, students and graduates continue to impact on 
public policy, enhance knowledge and promote best practice. The University continues to be influential in a range of areas 
including health and wellbeing, education, sport and environment among others. The University's initiatives, plans and goals 
in recent years have strengthened its commitment to equality, reconciliation and a fair and knowledgeable community.

Respected human rights campaigner Professor Tom Calma AO was reappointed as Chancellor of the University of Canberra in 
2017 for another three-year term. Professor Calma has held the position since 1 January 2014 and was the first Aboriginal 
man to become Chancellor of an Australian university. Professor Calma is an Aboriginal elder of the Kungarakan tribal group, 
a member of the Iwaidja tribal group and a champion for the rights, responsibilities and welfare of Aboriginal and Torres 
Strait Islander Australians.

Outreach and widening participation
The University is committed to student equity in higher education, providing opportunities to people from a range of 
backgrounds. The University understands that while enrolments have increased in recent years, participation and attainment 
rates among those in regional Australia remain low.








canberra.edu.au                                             1

                       Regional Inequality in Australia 
                           Submission 26

     UNIVERSITY OF                            DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
 44r. CANBERRA




With funding under the Higher Education Participation and Partnerships Program (HEPPP) the University delivers outreach 
initiatives through participating secondary schools across the ACT and regional NSW.

The Widening Participation Team includes current University of Canberra students and engages people from:

   • a rural and/or regional background;
   • an Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander background;
   • a history of financial disadvantage; and/or
   • little or no family experience of higher education.

Outreach and widening participation programs include the following: 

Aspire UC
Aspire UC is the University of Canberra's flagship rural and regional schools outreach program. Since 2010, Aspire UC has 
delivered a range of in-school activities to support the academic achievement and educational aspirations of students from 
rural and regional and financially disadvantaged backgrounds. Targeted, age-appropriate activities are offered in-school to 
students predominantly in Years 9-11. Participating schools have: limited family experience of higher education; a history of 
financial disadvantage; a rural and/or regional background; and Aboriginal or Torres Strait Islander background.

UC 4 Yourself university experience days
Complementing the in-school Aspire UC program, school students are offered the opportunity to visit the University of 
Canberra campus for a UC 4 Yourself University Experience Day. The days aim to:

   • give students exposure to and first-hand experience with a higher education environment, academics, current 
     students, facilities and support services
   • assist students to develop an understanding of the courses and possibilities available through university study
   • encourage students to make informed decisions about their futures and pathways
   • raise students' aspirations for higher education' assist students in identifying and overcoming barriers to higher 
     education;
   • smooth the transition between school and university
   • debunk common myths associated with studying at university

Students participating in the day take part in a range of activities designed to provide exposure to a higher education 
environment, including: engaging with current students; touring student accommodation facilities; participating in hands on 
workshops delivered by faculty members; exploring the campus, learning spaces and buildings; and; participating in the 
'Expo' to meet current staff and students and learn about a variety of course and disciplines that may align with post school 
dreams and pathways.

Stronger Smarter Schools Project (SSSP)
The Stronger Smarter Schools Project was a collaborative project in 2017 between the University of Canberra and the 
Stronger Smarter Institute and delivered six intensive professional learning programs to teachers and school executive 
members working in the ACT and regional NSW schools. Through the SSSP, University of Canberra and the Stronger Smarter 
Institute worked with teachers and school leaders to build their leadership capacity to deliver quality educational outcomes 
for Indigenous students and those from low SES backgrounds. Over 100 teachers participated in the program, and were 
asked to identify a local issue, or personal challenge to focus on. Teachers chose a variety of areas including staff 
relationships, school pride, teacher and student relationships, and relationships with Indigenous staff, students and




 canberra.edu.au                                             2

                       Regional Inequality in Australia 
                           Submission 26

     UNIVERSITY OF                            DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
 44. CANBERRA




community members. The professional learning programs had a profound impact on participating staff and have resulted in 
numerous examples of positive cultural changes in schools.

Australian Indigenous Mentoring Experience (AIME)
The University has a partnership with the Australian Indigenous Mentoring Experience (AIME). Aboriginal and Torres Strait 
Islander students studying at schools across the region are mentored by University of Canberra students as part of the AIME 
program. Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander school students are assisted to develop the skills, opportunities, belief and 
confidence to succeed in their education. The program encourages students to get involved and sign up as a mentor in the 
program and serve as a mentor to an Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander student studying in local and regional high 
schools. The University works alongside the Australian National University (ANU) to deliver AIME programs in the region, with 
the ANU working with Canberra-based Indigenous students and the University of Canberra focusing on Indigenous Australian 
students from schools across regional NSW, including Goulburn, Queanbeyan, Vass and Booroowa.

ACT-Indigenous Success Project
The ACT-Indigenous Success Project (ACTIS) engaged with local and regional students from 3 high schools (2 in the ACT, 1 in 
regional NSW) to deliver aspirations raising sessions to students in Years 9-10. The program also offered a University 
Pathways Program to students in Year 11-12 who completed a series of modules delivered by UC staff over two school terms. 
Students were challenged to think critically and reflect on their personal learning journey and receive academic preparation 
to commence university studies. Students who successfully completed the University Pathways Program were eligible to 
receive an offer for a University of Canberra degree program, and for entry to the ANU College Diploma program.

The Smith Family outreach support
The University supports a number of initiatives for The Smith Family Learning for Life students, providing in-kind and financial 
support. These events include the annual Graduation Ceremony, celebrating Learning for Life students who have graduated 
from high school or university study, scholarship support for school students and tertiary students, Tertiary Information 
Sessions, homework clubs for high school students and on-campus university experience days.

Aspire UC VIP Open Day experiences
The Aspire UC VIP Open Day caters for financially disadvantaged students and their families who live in regional areas who 
have limited awareness of higher education and have previously participated in the Aspire UC schools outreach program. The 
day is incorporated into the broader University of Canberra Open Day. The Aspire UC VIP Experience provides an inclusive, 
supported opportunity for students to meet staff, current students and familiarise students with the University environment. 
Open Day can be a daunting and overwhelming experience for rural and regional students with limited higher education 
experience. The VIP Open Day experience provides free lunch, access to Widening Participation staff and current students, 
and specialised tours through student accommodation and university facilities to support the participation of students in the 
Open Day experience.

Transitions forums
Widening Participation takes part in a range of transition forums in rural and regional schools, including Monaro High School 
in Cooma and Lake Ginninderra College in Canberra. The sessions are designed to assist students to transition to senior years 
of school, and to expand students' thinking about their future options.

Wreck Bay Community
Widening Participation has an informal partnership with the Wreck Bay Aboriginal community providing community support 
and engagement, most particularly through NAIDOC week celebrations.




canberra.edu.au                                             3

                       Regional Inequality in Australia 
                           Submission 26

AAA UNIVERSITY OF                            DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
 44. CANBERRA




Aurora
The University has a partnership with Aurora (The Aspiration Initiative) to provide academic enrichment for Aboriginal and 
Torres Strait Islander students, both prior to, and throughout their university studies. This program also includes support for 
students' families, a scholarships portal, and academic enrichment camps (one held at the University).

Other outreach programs
Widening Participation facilitates a range of outreach programs on an informal basis each year, designed to support the 
needs of schools that approach the University without participating in one of the major outreach programs. Students will 
generally participate in a campus tour, have a faculty-led hands on experience, and meet with current students to break 
down barriers to higher education. The University also provides tailored experiences for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander 
students on campus in partnership with the ACT Education Department.

Transformative education
While the University of Canberra has its main campus in the nation's capital, it serves as both a regional and global hub with 
students from all around the nation and the world.

More than fifteen percent of the University's domestic students come from a regional or remote background. Retention rates 
for these students at University of Canberra are above the sector average for all universities.

The University recognises the challenges faced by students from a regional background and has in place a number of 
initiatives including scholarships and support programs.

Student scholarships
University of Canberra regional students may receive support through scholarships. University and external scholarship 
opportunities for regional students include:

   • Deepwater Scholarship — total value of $15,000 per year for the duration of the degree, capped at $45,000 awarded 
     to young Australians from rural and remote areas
   • UniLodge UC Accommodation Scholarship - $4,000 awarded to financially disadvantaged students who are residing 
     in UniLodge accommodation at Bruce campus
   • UC Foundation Scholarship for Rural and Remote Students - $3,000
   • UC Foundation Scholarship for Indigenous Students - $3,000 awarded to financially disadvantaged Aboriginal and/or 
     Torres Strait Islander students
   • UC St Vincent De Paul Scholarship for Indigenous Students - $2,500 awarded to financially disadvantaged Aboriginal 
     and/or Torres Strait Islander students
   • Charles Perkins Scholarship for Undergraduate Indigenous Students - $2,000 awarded to financially disadvantaged 
     Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander students
   • Bobi Meyer Indigenous Scholarships - $15,000 awarded to financially disadvantaged Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait 
     Islander students
   • UC CIRI Scholarship - $5,000 awarded to financially disadvantaged Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander students
   • Generation One Scholarship - $4,000 awarded to Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander students
   • House Call Doctor Futures in Health Indigenous Scholarship - $10,000 awarded to Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait 
     Islander students in 2nd year of undergraduate study in health or medical field
   • Veolia Mulwaree Trust Scholarship - $3,000 awarded to financially disadvantaged students from a rural, regional or 
     remote area who are active within the community
   • Bendigo and Adelaide Bank 2018 Scholarship - $10,000 awarded to enrolled students who are academically 
     outstanding but disadvantaged, are from a rural and remote area




 canberra.edu.au                                            4

                       Regional Inequality in Australia 
                            Submission 26

ju UNIVERSITY OF                               DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
44. CANBERRA




  • Andrew F Dennis Rural Scholarship - $2,500 awarded to financially disadvantaged students from a rural, regional or 
    remote area studying Information Technology or Education
  • Stephen Parker Law Scholarship - $2,500 awarded to a student from underrepresented backgrounds in the 
    Australian legal profession
  ■ University of Canberra and John & Helen Grant Scholarship for Educational Leadership - $3,000 awarded to 
    financially disadvantaged students from a rural, regional or remote area showing leadership potential
  ■ University of Canberra College Scholarship for Rural and Remote Students - $2,500 awarded to financially 
    disadvantaged students from a rural, regional or remote area enrolled at the UC College or who have recently 
    articulated into a UC degree

UC Belong
The UC Belong program is aimed at commencing students and designed to enhance students' wellbeing and create a sense of 
belonging at the University. UC Belong includes the Peer Mentoring, Rural Student Support, and the Humanitarian Visa 
Student Support programs for students who have come to Australia as refugees.

Indigenous Student Success Program
The Indigenous Student Success Program (ISSP) delivered by the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet, commenced on 
1 January 2017 and provides funding to help students take on the demands of university and succeed. ISSP funding is 
particularly prioritised towards the support of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander students who are financially 
disadvantaged and/or from remote and regional areas.

University of Canberra Ngunnawal Centre
The University of Canberra Ngunnawal Centre is a key point of contact for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander students 
enrolled at the university. The Ngunnawal Centre liaises with students about educational progress and coordinates 
appropriate academic support in line with the ISSP funding guidelines (e.g. scholarships and tutorial assistance), and tracks 
student progress to support student success.

The Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Student Success Tutorial Program (formerly ITAS)
Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander students of the University of Canberra can receive up to 2 hours of tuition per unit of 
study each week for each unit (subject) for free. Upon approval, during examination periods tuition can be increased to an 
additional 5 hours of support per week.

Career Trackers Indigenous Internship Program
The University has a 10-year partnership between CareerTrackers, the University of Canberra and the Ngunnawal Centre that 
aims to create a community of students who share common aspirations and create role models to inspire future generations 
of university students.

The overarching principle of this 10x10 initiative (10 year agreement signed by 10 universities) is to formalise the pathways 
for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander university students into experiential learning opportunities and to work closely with 
CareerTrackers to achieve our mutual goal of improving the educational outcomes for Indigenous students.

This partnership aligns with the UC Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Strategic Plan 2017-2021, as the University continues 
to expand its regional reach and increase its partnerships with other local, national and international education institutions. It 
will particularly support and educate our students through the provision of flexible learning delivery environments.







canberra.edu.au                                                5

                      Regional Inequality in Australia 
                          Submission 26

JL, UNIVERSITY OF                            DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN

44. CANBERRA




The Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Foundation Program
The Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Foundation Program helps to build the skills needed for study at the University of 
Canberra. It is designed for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander students who do not meet University admission 
requirements but have a reasonable chance of success in higher education. The program is delivered through the UC College 
in close collaboration with the UC Ngunnawal Centre.

Clinical placements in regional communities
University of Canberra students undertake a broad range of clinical health placements in regional areas, including the far 
South Coast and Western New South Wales. This is In line with the Australian Government's commitment to improving 
access to health services for regional Australians.

Students undertaking regional clinical placements in Nursing, Midwifery and a range of allied health disciplines are 
supported by the University with additional funding to assist with travel and expenses.

Students undertaking Pharmacy placements in rural areas are financially supported with a bursary scheme run by the 
Pharmacy Guild of Australia.

Students undertaking Medical Radiation Science (Medical Imaging), as part of their clinical placement requirements, must 
attend a regional or rural placement. This allows students to experience radiographic practice, as well as health practices 
more generally, in a regional or rural setting. Students are supported to meet some of the cost of these placements through 
bursaries.

The nature of these placements means that students engage with regional communities in a variety of community health 
settings. Students undertaking regional placements access local accommodation and a full range of goods and services during 
this time. The number of University of Canberra students who travel to live and work in regional communities as part of their 
degree creates a positive economic and social impact.

Recent physiotherapy student placements in rural locations have included the following:

  ■ Increased capacity in Bega from 2-3 students per year (in 2013) to 30 per year (in 2018)
  ■ Investment in student accommodation in Bega
  • Student led physiotherapy clinic in Moruya/Pambula
  • Formal working arrangements formed with the Southcoast Health
  ■ Increased placements in Orange to 32 students in 2017
  • Strengthening links with East-Maitland Community Health
  • Future placements planned in Gilgandra
  • Ongoing placements in Tasmania (Burnie, Launceston and Hobart)

Faculty of Health Clinical Educators workshops provide valuable continuing professional development opportunities for 
regional and rural clinical staff involved in clinical education of University of Canberra health students.

Engaging students
The University encourages students to engage with regional Australia, offering a number of unique transformative 
opportunities. Examples include:









canberra.edu.au                                            6

                      Regional Inequality in Australia 
                           Submission 26

jta UNIVERSITY OF                            DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
q-r CANBERRA




Athlete in Residence
In 2017 Olympic race walker and Yuin woman Beki Smith was announced as the University of Canberra's Athlete in 
Residence, making her the first Aboriginal or Torres Strait Islander person appointed to the role. Mrs Smith, the latest 
high-profile sportsperson to take on the unique role worked side by side with staff and students, giving them an 
opportunity to learn from her experiences as a professional athlete. The Olympian was involved in projects embedded 
within a host of disciplines and across all faculties.

Northern Territory Rural Health Promotion Scholarship
A University of Canberra physiotherapy student was recently awarded a Rural Health Promotion Scholarship from the NT 
Primary Health Network. This representative will join a team of 8 health students who will tour remote high schools to 
encourage students to consider a career in allied health.

The New Colombo Plan - overseas opportunities for regional students
More than 400 students studying at the University of Canberra will have the opportunity to complete part of their degree 
overseas in 2018 as part of the Federal Government's New Colombo Plan (NCP) Mobility Program. The program provides 
students with opportunities to undertake internships and study programs outside of Australia.

The University has been awarded $1.3 million in new funding to continue supporting undergraduate students to study and 
undertake internships in the Indo-Pacific region in 2018.

A group of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander students recently spent time with Indigenous Fijians on a study trip funded 
under the New Colombo Plan initiative. The program consisted of ten days of cultural activities, including visiting 
Indigenous Fijian enterprises and cultural institutions and sites, and meeting with villagers to learn about the strength and 
resilience of their Indigenous knowledge. The program enriched their learning experience and the students returned to 
Australia with a good understanding of Indigenous Fijian knowledge, and the associated benefits of sharing these 
knowledge systems globally and with their own Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander communities.




Mission-oriented problem-solving research
The University of Canberra has had long-standing excellence in mission-oriented problem-solving research. While the 
University is anchored in Australia's capital, we work with government, business and industry to serve our communities and 
the nation.

The University undertakes research that solves real-world problems with much of this having application in regional 
Australia. Examples include the following:

Murray-Darling Basin Futures Collaborative Research Network (MDBfutures)
MDBfutures was a collaborative research network led by the University of Canberra between 2011 and 2015. Its research 
contributed to knowledge for the sustainable development of the Murray-Darling Basin and building resilience. The 
University, along with network partners, brought together academic disciplines and collaborators to this complex task. The 
research achievements of MDBfutures set a foundation for further work in this important key area for regional Australia.

The four core themes of MDBfutures were:





canberra.edu.au                                             7

                       Regional Inequality in Australia 
                            Submission 26

JAL UNIVERSITY OF                               DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
44: CANBERRA




Drivers of change - understanding and integrating the economic, social, health and environmental drivers of change in the 
Murray-Darling Basin
Environmental watering and allocation - understanding and optimising water requirements, diversity, ecosystem services 
and productive water uses in the Murray-Darling Basin
Better governance, planning and management - innovative approaches for the Murray-Darling Basin 
Synthesis - integrating water, communities and environment

UC Collaborative Indigenous Research Initiative (CIRI)
The University of Canberra Collaborative Indigenous Research Initiative (UC CIRO, launched in June 2014 is a network of 
researchers committed to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander research that fosters local, national and international 
partnerships.

UC CIRI has positive effect on growing the University's capacity, impact and reputation in Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander 
research and in building a research environment that is supportive of Indigenous peoples, cultures and achievements. To 
date UC CIRI has provided funding to 10 projects focused on issues important to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander 
communities.

The projects consist of multidisciplinary teams that include Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander researchers and were 
developed in consultation with Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander communities. It is anticipated that some of these 
projects will grow into national projects with significant and tangible outcomes to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander 
communities. The focus of these projects has included:

  • Cultural Heritage;
  • Health and health practices;
  • Education;
  • Tourism; and
  • Environments of cultural significance.

These projects are showing significant outcomes in the form of:

  • increasing Indigenous knowledge (the Cullunghutti project's impact on the official Indigenous historical archives of 
    the Nowra which are held at the State Library of NSW);
  ■ book chapters and publications accepted in top rated journals (such as BMJ Open);
  ■ developing innovative research methodologies (the Journal of Australian Studies expressed an interest in the 
    publishing a special issue based around the Cullunghutti team's symposia);
  • improving cultural awareness at University of Canberra and wider (Local community members have told the Bundian 
    Way team that their teaching methods are helping to break down the cultural walls and is encouraging cultural 
    awareness); and
  • opening up opportunities for the communities with whom the research teams collaborate wider (Salt Springs team 
    in the Northern Territory have been taking local primary school students to their field site with microscopes giving 
    children in the from Ltyentye Apurte community the opportunity for real scientific study at a site of local 
    significance).







canberra.edu.au                                                 8

                      Regional Inequality in Australia 
                          Submission 26

     UNIVERSITY OF                           DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
 44. CANBERRA




Apmere Atyenhe Ltyentye Apurte (Our Home Santa Teresa)

In 2017, under its Visitor Program, UC CIRI in conjunction with the Faculty of Arts and Design (FAD), hosted Dr Anita Heiss 
as a Postdoctoral Fellow (Writing and Indigenous Studies). Dr Heiss is a renowned Indigenous author of both fiction and 
non-fiction books.
As part of Dr Heiss' research with the University of Canberra, she worked with Arrente students from Ltyentye Apurte 
community to develop a greater love of literacy and art. Students gained insight into how books are created through each 
step of the process — writing, editing, production, release, providing them a better understanding and appreciation of 
literature and literacy.
The students produced the picture book Apmere Atyenhe Ltyentye Apurte (Our Home Santa Teresa), a collection of 
writing created during workshops run at Ltyentye Apurte Catholic School by Dr Anita Heiss and Leecee Carmichael - with 
the support of the University of Canberra, and in collaboration with Gilimbaa Creative Agency. Dr Heiss and Ms Carmichael 
also demonstrated to the students the diversity of First Nations peoples (coming from cities with coastal and regional ties) 
and both women acted as role models in terms of education and self-employment.
This project demonstrates the University commitment to quality literacy programs for remote communities. Improving 
literacy skills among Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander students increases their life opportunities and enhances their 
wellbeing. Working together bringing children into the creative process of storytelling and building the capacity of 
students in literacy and book production is another step closer to reconciliation in Australia.
Thanks to the enthusiasm the students have for storytelling; their book gives readers all around the country a wonderful 
insight into their lives in Ltyentye Apurte and all that matters to them. The student's stories and illustrations demonstrate 
the life experiences of the young authors in their community, including what they do for fun, their happiest moments, who 
their heroes are and what places they consider special or sacred to them.



Canberra Urban and Regional Futures
Canberra Urban and Regional Futures (CURF) is a joint initiative between the University of Canberra, the ACT Government 
and the Australian National University's Climate Change Institute, which offers a research platform on urban and regional 
issues. CURF maintains a research program on local and national issues, publishing a series of working papers on climate 
change adaptation and urban renewal, journal articles and conference presentations. CURF completed several national 
climate change adaptation projects funded by the National Climate Change Adaptation Facility. Members of the CURF team 
encouraged debate on issues of community interest at local and national forums. Members regularly contributed to The 
Conversation. CURF hosted several flagship seminars aligned with each of the four CURF themes: climate change and 
sustainability; settlements and infrastructure; health and wellbeing; and green growth. The Annual CURF Forum brought 
together leaders in government, industry and the wider Australian capital region to discuss knowledge gaps and potential 
research solutions aligned with the CURF themes.

STEM Education Research Centre — Spatial Reasoning Project
The Spatial Reasoning Project aims to better understand the influence of spatial reasoning on school mathematics and has 
received a grant from the ARC. For the most disadvantaged students, opportunities to develop such reasoning skills are 
limited as they are typically not taught in schools. The consequences of low numeracy and spatial reasoning are profound in 
terms of quality adult life. The project investigates the role and nature of spatial reasoning in students' mathematics 
development and substantiates the extent to which a spatial learning program has a long-term effect on educationally 
disadvantaged students' mathematics performance and reasoning. The first phase saw fieldwork conducted in rural and 
remote Indigenous Australian schools. This involved the development of three classroom activities focusing on spatial





canberra.edu.au                                            9

                       Regional Inequality in Australia 
                            Submission 26

a.4 UNIVERSITY OF                              DISTINCTIVE BY DESIGN
44 CANBERRA




reasoning that are designed for the specific context they are being implemented in (rural, remote, low socio-economic status 
[SES], culturally diverse, high SES).

Supporting Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander communities to tackle smoking
Professor Rachel Davey and Associate Professor Penney Upton are members of the National Best Practice Unit Tackling 
Indigenous Smoking (NBPU TIS), a Federal Government funded consortium established in 2015 to provide tailored support to 
organisations funded under the national TIS program for Regional Grants. Led by Ninti One, the consortium works with 
regional community organisations on TIS-related matters by providing education, training and development, and research 
support. This work addresses the significant health inequalities associated with high smoking rates seen in Aboriginal and 
Torres Strait Islander communities and includes the following activities:

  • Enabling access to research, information and resources on tobacco control;
  • Assisting with the development of Action Plans for TIS activities;
  ■ Collaborating on the development of local measures for monitoring the impact of TIS activities;
  • Providing relevant training and networking opportunities (such as brief intervention training, smoking cessation 
    workshops).

Support to regional communities across Australia is provided through a variety of mechanisms including face to face regional 
workshops and local organisation visits, telelinks, webinars and an on-line resource and information centre developed by UC- 
HRI and hosted by the third consortium partner Australian Indigenous HealthlnfoNet, Edith Cowan University, Perth. 
Examples of the support provided to regional communities can be found on the Tackling Indigenous Smoking Portal 
developed by the Unit.

Enhancing aspirations for STEM careers in rural, regional and remote communities
Associate Professor Philip Roberts, Faculty of Education is undertaking research on aspirations for STEM careers in rural, 
regional and remote communities. This project explores the relationship between rural students' understanding of the role of 
STEM subjects in rural careers, their aspirations for rural STEM careers, how this influences senior school subject selection, 
and subsequent impact on university study. By understanding the needs of the rural sector related to STEM, and students' 
perceptions of rural industry, this project provides the basis of a strategy for highlighting the relevance of STEM to rural 
careers and innovation that can be used to encourage students to take relevant STEM subjects in their senior studies and 
subsequently university.

Regional Wellbeing Survey
Associate Professor Jacki Schirmer, Institute for Applied Ecology and Health Research Institute continues to oversee the 
Regional Wellbeing Survey annually. First conducted in 2013, the Regional Wellbeing Survey examines the views of 13,000 
rural and regional Australians about the livability and resilience of their community, and their own wellbeing and resilience. It 
covers topics ranging from understanding how to support carers living in the bush, to identifying the impacts of poor Internet 
connectivity, and understanding how events such as droughts, floods and environmental policy change affect rural 
communities. This project provides an evidence base to inform public policy and resource management.

Understanding land use conflict in rural Australia
Professor Linda Botterill, Faculty of Business, Government and Law undertakes research in land use conflict in rural Australia. 
This project focuses on how conflicts over rural land uses, such as mining and wind farms, can be better addressed through 
understanding the underlying values held by protagonists. It seeks to identify the key values that influence attitudes towards 
rural Australia and the extent to which these limit policy options. More broadly than agricultural policy, a values analytic





canberra.edu.au                                               10

