                 Regional Inequality in Australia 
                     Submission 56



                      itzk'
                      Itikatts4011' -

                     -44111111111Mommirm.......
                       Shire of

                  Gunnedah
                    Land of Opportunity

Mr Mark Fitt
Committee Secretary
Senate Economic References Committee 
GPO Box 6100
Parliament House
CANBERRA ACT 2600


30 April 2018


Dear Mr Fitt

   Re: Senate Economics References Committee — Invitation to submit an inquiry into the 
          indicators of, and impact of, regional inequality in Australia

I write on behalf of Gunnedah Shire Council following an invitation for submission into regional 
inequality in Australia.

Gunnedah Shire is located in the North West Slopes Region of north-west New South Wales, about 450 
kilometres north of the Sydney CBD, and about 650 kilometres south of the Brisbane CBD. Gunnedah 
Shire shares borders with Narrabri Shire, Tamworth Regional Council, Liverpool Plains and 
Warrumbungle Shire. A largely rural area, the Gunnedah Shire encompasses a total land area of 5,000 
square kilometres.

Gunnedah Shire is situated in the heart of North West NSW on the banks of the Namoi River and is the 
gateway to one of the most productive and prime agricultural regions in Australia — the Liverpool Plains. 
Gunnedah also has coal mining in the western corner.

The Shire has an estimated residential population of 12,551. Gunnedah has a high percentage of 
disadvantaged people with 21% of households represented in the low income category, earning less 
than $650 per week. 12.8% of our population are Aboriginal compared to 5.5% across NSW and 2.8% 
nationally. The SEIFA Index for Gunnedah Shire measures at 956 and ranks us 85 out of 131 Local 
Government Areas measured in NSW.

Gunnedah Shire's Gross Regional Product was $0.63 billion in the year ending June 2016, declining 
1.5% from the previous year. Agriculture is the dominate industry making Gunnedah highly exposed to 
the boom and bust cycles synonymous with an agriculture industry driven by both climate and market 
impacts. Mining and industry servicing mining is also a large sector of the Gunnedah economy, 
although growing, this sector has been known to be volatile due to elasticity of pricing and changing 
market conditions.

Our Shire can provide a high quality of life, with access to more affordable housing, and some quality 
schools, cultural and sporting pursuits. Although we can see the benefits of living regionally there are a 
number of services that are inadequate compared to our city counterparts and are hampering further 
economic growth. There are challenges in relation to attracting new families and retaining school 
leavers. Local businesses are struggling to remain competitive in the global business environment; our 
region is experiencing a significant skills shortage across all employment sectors. The skills shortage 
has meant that there are hundreds of jobs that cannot be filled.




                    Gunnedah Shire Council 
             63 Elgin Street, PO Box 63 GUNNEDAH NSW 2380 
                 Tel: (02) 6740 2100 Fax: (02) 6740 2119 
                 Email: council@infogunnedah.com.au 
                  Web: www.gunnedah.nsw.gov.au

                Regional Inequality in Australia 
                    Submission 56

Senate Economics References Committee — Invitation to submit an inquiry into the indicators of, and 
impact of, regional inequality in Australia
GUNNEDAH SHIRE COUNCIL                      PAGE 2

Gunnedah District Hospital is a very dated facility. Although upgraded in 2015/16, a new hospital is 
required to meet the needs of the growing community. There are some basic services that are critically 
lacking for example; the Hospital does not have a Dialysis machine; diabetics have to travel to 
Tamworth (one hour drive) for treatment. Gunnedah has trouble attracting doctors and also needs 
additional allied health and dental services. The lack of quality medical facilities and services in 
Gunnedah was identified by both Council, local businesses and the mining sector as a constraint to 
attracting new residents to the area.

The Gunnedah High School is in need of assistance. The school used to educate approximately 800 
students, however despite the growth in population, current enrolment is less than 400 students. The 
reduction of students has meant the reduction of subject choices and has in turn meant lower High 
School certificate marks reducing future choices for our young people. Gunnedah High School has also 
raised concerns as they have had difficulty attracting new teachers to Gunnedah. There are now four 
busloads of students per day going to Tamworth to seek higher quality education. Our school leavers 
figures are of concern overall, 49.8% of the population left school at Year 10 or below, and only 32.0% 
went on to complete Year 12 or equivalent, compared with 33.5% and 52.1% respectively for New 
South Wales.

The Gunnedah TAFE facility is not meeting the training needs that our business community requires. 
More must be done by TAFE to train potential candidates to be ready to fill our large amount of vacant 
roles. Another notable restraint in the service provided by TAFE; although agriculture is the main 
economic activity, there are no agricultural courses available at the local TAFEs. In Gunnedah, where 
mining, fabrication and manufacturing are significant activities, there are no mining, construction or 
metal trades courses at Gunnedah TAFE, and no opportunity locally for students who have gained 
basic metal trades certificates through the Trade Training Centre at Gunnedah High School, to gain 
further qualifications. Access to mainstream construction trades (building, carpentry) courses are also 
needed.

Our residents travel long distances compared to our metropolitan counterparts. As many businesses or 
Government departments are reducing employees in regional centres, it is becoming more common to 
travel large distances for meetings and appointments. Increased travel times have significant impacts 
due to high costs of fuel prices and air travel. Time spent out of the business is also detrimental for 
productivity. Travel times also have impacts on freight costs, a constraint for growth for our business 
sector. If Gunnedah Shire residents need to travel to Sydney for an appointment their public transport 
choices are; the Country Link train service which is an eight hour trip (five hours by car) or they must fly 
from Tamworth (one hour drive away) and one way tickets can cost up to $400.

Gunnedah Shire is significantly held back due to poor telecommunications coverage and slow internet 
speeds, lack of reliability and relatively high cost of internet services. Mobile coverage is also patchy 
outside of the Gunnedah town limits and villages. Poor telecommunication infrastructure is rendering it 
difficult for producers to conduct business (eg access banking, down and upload forms and perform 
teleconferences etc), utilise digital-based technology and access information, on-line training etc, and 
trade on-line internationally. Some of our farmers who run their businesses from their farm have 
accessed the Sky-Muster NBN internet satellites; although these have been known to be notoriously 
slow and only offer data plans of up to 140GB per month. It is not uncommon to see some of our 
farmers updating their iPad software when they are at McDonalds or booked into a hotel in Sydney as 
they have used up their meagre data allowance. It is increasingly difficult to run businesses or embark 
on further study with substandard internet. Why should country people have deal with a lesser service 
compared to the city?

As an organisation Gunnedah Shire Council pays the price of being situated regionally. In some cases, 
in order to attract specialised skills we have had to compensate staff members with travel and 
accommodation costs. Capital works projects also attract additional costs of construction due to our 
regional location it can be assumed that projects will be 15% higher to construct than in metropolitan 
areas.


                   Gunnedah Shire Council 
             63 Elgin Street, PO Box 63, GUNNEDAH NSW 2380 
                Tel: (02) 6740 2100 Fax: (02) 6740 2119 
                Email: couneilAinfogunnedah.com.au 
                 Web: www.infogunnedah.com.au

               Regional Inequality in Australia 
                   Submission 56


Senate Economics References Committee — Invitation to submit an inquiry into the indicators of, and 
impact of, regional inequality in Australia
GUNNEDAH SHIRE COUNCIL                      PAGE 3

In order to reduce the divide between regional and metropolitan areas increased investment into 
enabling infrastructure urgently required. Gunnedah would hugely benefit from improvements to the 
Gunnedah District Hospital, investment in the schools in Gunnedah and TAFE. Without quality health 
and education Gunnedah is struggling to attract more new residents as they do not have confidence in 
our services. Gunnedah should also not be held back by poor Internet and telecommunications, 
investment to bring us up to speed is urgently needed.

Another way of incentivising people to move to regional Australia would be through reductions of tax 
concessions on payroll tax, stamp duty, land tax utility charges and fuel costs. Tax incentives could 
provide businesses with an opportunity to set up or expand in Gunnedah and thereby reduce the 
burden of these costs for local residents and businesses and therefore will contribute significantly to the 
creation of an economic environment that is both viable and sustainable in the long term.

More must be done to promote rural and regional living to encourage decentralisation and skills 
migration. Our cities are becoming increasingly crowded and Gunnedah in particular must see some 
new, fresh faces in town to help us to fill our job vacancies and combat our skills shortage. If we do not  
see an influx of a skilled population we risk economic decline and miss out on potential unprecedented 
growth.

Feel free to contact me if you have further enquiries with regard to our submission.


Yours faithfully





Eric Groth
GENERAL MANAGER

Contact: 
eg:ch

































                  Gunnedah Shire Council 
            63 Elgin Street, PO Box 63, GUNNEDAH NSW 2380 
               Tel: (02) 6740 2100 Fax: (02) 6740 2119 
               Email: councilinfogunnedah.com.au 
                Web: www.infogunnedah.com.au

