                                       Regional Inequality in Australia 


                                             Submission 65

                                                                         abn 56 044 159 537 



                                                     Civic Centre           p 1300 292 442 



                                             Cnr Baylis & Morrow Sts        f 02 6926 9199 


ACity of                                              PO Box 20     e council@waggansw.gov.au 
  .......


1■AIN Wagga Wagga                           Wagga Wagga NSW 2650     w www.wagga.nsw.gov.au











         30 April 2018













         The Chair



         Senate Economics Reference Committee 



         Po Box 6100



         Parliament House



         CANBERRA ACT 2600








         Dear Honourable Committee Members








         Re: Inquiry into the indicators of, and impact of, regional inequality in 



         Australia








         Thank you for your request for submissions in relation to indicators of, and 



         impact of, regional inequality in Australia.








         The purpose of this letter is to make submissions on behalf of Wagga 



         Wagga City Council.








         At the outset, I observe that most of the issues we identify have been 



         touched upon previously in one form or another. Sadly, Government 



         (including Local Government) has not achieved any tangible level of 



         success in stemming the growing inequalities between metropolitan areas 



         at regional areas.








         Experiences of individuals and localities of unequal access to 



         opportunities and unequal outcomes in non-metropolitan areas:








         Education








         It is appropriate to commence with the disparities in education available to 



         regional areas in comparison to metro areas. The youth of regional areas 



         are fundamental to the future success of regions however, they suffer 



         perhaps the greatest inequality of futures in comparison to metropolitan 



         counter parts.








         This statement is true in relation to opportunities for high quality education 



         at secondary school levels which flows through to tertiary opportunities.








         Inequalities are clearly identifiable in:








             •  access to skilled teachers (meaning top teachers with a record for 



                lifting student performance and growth)




             •  high quality academic role models and mentors




             •  instilling a sense of attaining high achievement in commercial, 



                leadership or health specialists (to name a few)

              Regional Inequality in Australia 
                  Submission 65

Senate Economics Reference Committee
                                     2

This point is aimed at identifying that the environment of metropolitan 
students creates a more optimistic sense of future in comparison to regional 
schooling

A comparison of ATAR results will show a bias towards metropolitan areas. 
This is perhaps a measure of the influences discussed above. What this 
means, however, is that the youth are not nurtured to the same level as 
metropolitan youth.

The inequality in education continues to tertiary learning opportunities in 
specific courses. There is disparity in the quality of opportunities (some top 
tier law firms have a preference for graduates from particular law schools 
which are• hard to enter from a regional background due to the ATAR 
requirements and the cost).

Industry

Regional areas should have a high level of parity with metropolitan areas in 
relation to industry due to the relative availability and affordability of land. 
Unfortunately this is not the case, primarily due to neglect in infrastructure 
initiatives. This issue is being addressed to some degree in NSW.

The Government has been slow to actively pursue industry in NSW with 
other states often securing new opportunities due to aggressive 
inducements and facilitation.

Further inequalities which could each be discussed at length, include the 
following:

 • Narrow entertainment options for youth — this disparity leads to 
   reduced social and motor skills. In the long term it creates a negative 
   environment in regional areas
 • Lack of Police which are not allocated to reflect problem areas
 • Transport options — all options are expensive and generally harder 
   to access
 • Local public transport is generally a poor service which is not used
 • Medical practitioners — availability of medical practitioners in regional 
   areas is incomparable to metropolitan areas. This produces long 
   waiting times.
 • Local Government Rating Base — metropolitan is more favourable 
   than regional due to high density premises producing more local 
   government income for metropolitan areas. This is compounded by 
   large areas of regional NSW being unrateable land, eg: forestry with 
   roads that still need to be maintained.

             Regional Inequality in Australia 
                Submission 65

Senate Economics Reference Committee
                                 3

Experiences of Individuals and localities of unequal access to opportunities 
and unequal outcomes in non-metropolitan areas:

   • There are poorer outcomes for disadvantaged youth in regional 
     settings including but not limited to:

      o lower education outcomes (year 12 or equivalent in 
        Wagga 43.7% comparative to greater Sydney 60%)
      o higher rates of juvenile crime (in Wagga representation of 
        10-17 year olds in break and enter, steal from motor 
        vehicle, malicious damage correlates to 58%, 47% and 
        21% compared to Sydney LGA being 7%, 10% and 8%)
      o higher incidents of teenage pregnancy
      o higher rates of methamphetamines (ice) use in regional 
        locations

   • Health Care - specialised services are limited or not available. 
     Choice is limited to no or one provider in the private sector where 
     costs become an obstacle to access (examples include but are 
     not limited to; cancer care, transgender healthcare, LGBTIQ 
     support services, psychiatric services, refugees, substance 
     abuse, teenage mothers or mothers to be).

   • Wagga Wagga based domestic violence services , have raised 
     concerns regarding the limited availability of choice in legal aid 
     and supports eg. Practicing solicitors. Women escaping domestic 
     violence are also limited to only one domestic violence liaison 
     officer in police and minimal access to transport, particularly out 
     of business hours.

Poor allocation of State/Commonwealth funding to one provider for vast 
areas. Allocation demonstrates minimal understanding of the geographic 
capacity to operationalise direct service provision.

An example is the recent allocation of the Human Settlement Service 
Program contract to Red Cross to service Wollongong, Canberra, Wagga 
Wagga, Albury and other areas, where the coordination of the service 
delivery (specifically for recruitment of volunteers) is based in Wollongong 
and therefore locally in Wagga Wagga they have been unable to recruit the 
numbers of volunteers required

Views on the causes of inequality between regions especially between 
capital cities and other areas.

                         Regional Inequality in Australia 
                               Submission 65

Senate Economics Reference Committee
                                                                4

Policy settings, which could help address inequality between regions:

   •  Back policy with resourcing and allocation of funding where required. 
      For example the recent policy and implementation for Safe Haven 
      Enterprise Visa Holders required (SHEV) holders reside in Regional 
      Settings for periods of time, however minimal consideration has been 
      given to availability and or barriers to services, education, transport 
      and employment in Regional Settings.

   •  Policy makers need an increased understanding of Regional settings 
      and should apply a lens /formula to ensure allocation of 
      funding/policy /program resources based on considerations of 
      existence of transport and current service type within a certain radius 
      and not always based on volume 'of people. An example is the 
      Future Directions Policy set by NSW Family and Community 
      Services (FAGS) which seeks to ensure increased access to 
      services, education, employment and reduction of high density social 
      housing for persons requiring social housing. Limited application of 
      these highly valued principles are being applied locally in Wagga 
      Wagga and the local FACS office has for the past 2 years appeared 
      to have some degree of disconnection to head office to determine 
      any plans for application in the City.

   •  Increased investment in Regional Tourism infrastructure and 
      services/community infrastructure in particular cultural and 
      recreational/arts, cultural  and     community     wellbeing 
      programs/services to incentivise professionals to live and work in 
      Regional Settings.

   •  Improved communication and collaboration around key areas of 
      Interest between State and Commonwealth government to reduce 
      duplication around local areas of interest. More agility and flexibility 
      in program/policy/funding allocation based on local needs.

   •  Applications of funding/policy/program frameworks, which are 
      qualitative, and not quantative especially in the human services 
      sector to reduce focus on 'incidents of service' and ensure 'quality of 
      service' outcomes in the human services sector.

Views on the causes of inequality between regions, especially 
between capital cities and other areas

The causes of inequality between regional areas and metropolitan areas 
must be considered with regard to a transport factor.

To some degree, the problem can be summarised by observing a disparity 
or in equality in "opportunity" in regional areas which was not apparent 
historically. An historical review would reveal that in the past, regional areas 
had a sense of opportunity which was perhaps equal to metropolitan areas 
(albeit different).

              Regional Inequality in Australia 
                  Submission 65

Senate Economics Reference Committee
                                     5

In 2018, through poor policy and a poor appreciation for the impacts of 
change, we have far less opportunity in regional areas in comparison to 
metropolitan areas. This can be measured by reference to education, 
health, career opportunities, entertainment, wealth opportunities, security of 
employment, government services.

For decades we have focussed on level playing fields for investment, 
development and innovation. It is submitted that this consciousness is 
misplaced and is the single government driver of inequality between areas 
in our country. A bias towards "unequal playing fields" to achieve equality 
between metropolitan areas and regional areas should be considered to 
balance "opportunity" between these two areas.

Analysis of the economics of regional inequality, including wider 
impacts

Data from the latest Census allows us to analyse levels of inter-regional and 
intra-regional levels of inequality. The Wagga Wagga LGA has a score of 
944 across the Index of Relative Socio-Economic Disadvantage, a rank of 
44/134 NSW LGA's sampled for this index compiled from 17 Census 
variables including income, education, unemployment, skills and cost of 
living (source .id). This indicates a moderate level of inequality when 
compared to other NSW LGA's.

However further analysis of smaller areas within the Wagga Wagga LGA 
indicates mixed and more diverse results regarding inequality. The suburb 
of Ashmont has a Relative Socio-Economic Disadvantage index of 788 
according to latest Census data, and is considerably more disadvantaged 
than areas such as Springvale which has an index score of 1091. These 
high levels of inter-regional and intra-regional inequality are of high concern 
to this Council.

Inequality between large urban centres and regional areas is a result of both 
macroeconomic and local factors. Lower endowments of natural resources, 
larger geographical distances, weaker connectivity to major growth centres 
and people, weaker ICT infrastructure, and lower private and public 
investments skew the distribution of growth to major cities and weaken 
regional competitiveness. The importance of fiscal tax and spend policy 
should also not be under-estimated in driving distribution of wealth and 
income.

At the local level, several additional factors further re-enforce inequality. 
These local factors include weak industry attraction, low skills levels, lower 
educational attainment, poor English and language skills, lower paying 
occupations, and lower job creation or hours available to workers. Other 
factors driving intra-regional inequality include poor housing affordability, a 
higher relative cost of living, poor connectivity (local transport), low 
government investment, and untargeted Local Government spending (need 
to maintain roads is a drain on spending committed to other areas including 
those to promote more social cohesion).

              Regional Inequality in Australia 
                  Submission 65

Senate Economics Reference Committee
                                     6

The impacts of regional inequality are weaker economic, social and health 
outcomes. Economic impacts are higher unemployment, higher 
underemployment, weaker productivity, lower income levels, higher debt 
burdens, and the inability to attract key workers (Doctors, Professionals) to 
drive population. growth.

Social impacts include higher crime levels — drug use, theft, domestic 
violence, ice, car offences, and a lack of social cohesion. Finally, health 
impacts include higher levels of medical intervention needed, poor diet, 
higher demand for mental health and other support services.

The Wagga Wagga LGA suggests there is an opportunity for several policy 
interventions aimed at growing regional economies and lowering inequality 
between major urban centres, and lowering inequality within the LGA itself.

 1. Fiscal Policy reform: To attract more businesses to set up or expand 
   into the regions, relocation grants could be introduced alongside 
   corporate tax reductions for those setting up in key economic sectors 
   within designated regional enterprise zones.
 2. Incentivising key people to relocate to the regions: Boosting 
   population growth in the regions will take pressure off urban centres 
   experiencing infrastructural deficits, and provide spillover effects into 
   supporting economic sectors employing lower socio-economic 
   groups including retail, construction, transport, logistics and food 
   processing sectors. Relocation grants would incentivise people to 
   make the move to a regional area.
 3. A co-ordinated and focussed Regional Investment Strategy which 
   increases investment in key infrastructure including transport, supply 
   chain connectivity, ICT, utilities and other social infrastructure.
 4. Decentralisation of Government departments: Regional areas offer a 
   loWer cost advantage for Government departments.
 5. Investing in Education and Skills including TAFE based key courses.
 6. Building connectivity between the regions including increased 
   funding for regional airports, and acceleration of high-speed rail 
   program.
 7. Removing the burden on local budgets of maintaining large roads 
   budgets across wide geographic areas to allow increased funding for 
   targeted local program promoting more social cohesion.

Adopting these policy interventions will boost regional competitiveness and 
see the untapped potential across regional Australia and the Wagga Wagga 
LGA unleashed, driving growth and employment, and narrowing inter- 
regional and intra-regional inequality. This in turn will drive better economic, 
social cohesion and health outcomes across regional communities.

Yours faithfully




Peter Thompson 
General Manager

