                    Regional Inequality in Australia 
                       Submission 84



            Australian Government

            Department of Communications and the Arts



                                         Secretary

      PDR ID: EC18-000443








      Senator Chris letter
      Chair
      Senate Economics References Committee 
      PO Box 6100
      Parliament House
      CANBERRA ACT 2600


      Dear Chair


      Inquiry into the indicators of, and impact of, regional inequality in Australia


      The Department of Communications and the Arts welcomes the opportunity to make a 
      submission to the Committee's inquiry into the indicators of, and impact of, regional       inequality in Australia. The Department's submission to the inquiry is at Attachment A.
      inequality in Australia. The Department's submission to the inquiry is at Attachment A.
.

      Yours sincerely






      Mike Mrdak AO



     to May 2018



























                   GPO Box 2154 Canberra ACT 2601 Australia 
               • Telephone: 02 6271 1872 ■ Website: cornmunications.gov.au • arts.gov.au

                Regional Inequality in Australia 
                    Submission 84


                                     Attachment A




Inquiry into the indicators of, and impact of, regional inequality in
Australia
Submission from the Department of Communications and the Arts

The Department of Communications and the Arts has responsibility for a number of policies, 
programs, and initiatives that contribute to addressing regional inequality in Australia.

Access to telecommunications services is an important means of reducing regional inequality. 
Australia's vast geography and widely-dispersed population make it challenging to deliver 
affordable high speed broadband services to rural and regional areas. The rollout of the 
National Broadband Network (NBN) is meeting these challenges and improving business, 
social, education and health outcomes for people throughout Australia. The Australian 
Government is also taking steps to ensure broadband services continue to be available to all 
Australians no matter where they live.

The arts sector plays an important role in supporting sustainable and vibrant regional 
communities. The Government delivers a range of programs designed to increase 
participation in, and access to, Australia's arts and culture through developing and supporting 
cultural expression. These programs support and enhance arts and cultural practices and 
experiences in regional and remote communities that build human capital, enhance local 
workforce skills, and improve employment arrangements.

Infrastructure

National Broadband Network

The rollout of the NBN in rural and regional areas is the most significant public investment in 
improving regional communications undertaken in Australia. In addition to providing NBN 
fixed line broadband services to approximately 2.5 million regional premises, the 
Government is investing more than $2 billion in capital expenditure on nbn's fixed wireless 
network and approximately $2 billion on the Sky Muster Satellite service.

When planning the rollout, nbn is required to prioritise locations that are poorly served, to the 
extent commercially and operationally feasible. To achieve these objectives, nbn is rolling 
out a multi-technology mix network, which uses the technology best matched to each area of 
Australia. The multi-technology mix has enabled nbn to roll out its network to metropolitan 
and regional Australia more quickly and cost-effectively. When the rollout NBN is complete 
in 2020, all Australian homes and businesses will have access to services capable of 
delivering peak wholesale broadband speeds of at least 25 megabits per second.

Statutory infrastructure provider
To guarantee that broadband services are provided to premises after the NBN rollout is 
complete, the Government has legislation before the Parliament that will place 'statutory 
infrastructure provider' (SIP) requirements on NBN Co Limited (nbn) and other carriers 
where appropriate. The SIP requirements will require nbn, or another carrier, to connect 
premises to a superfast broadband network on reasonable request. This will provide industry 
and consumers with certainty that all premises in Australia, regardless of their location, will 
have access to infrastructure that supports the delivery of superfast broadband.

                Regional Inequality in Australia 
                   Submission 84







Regional Broadband Scheme
The legislation will also establish the Regional Broadband Scheme (RBS), which will secure 
long term funding for nbn's fixed wireless and satellite infrastructure. These networks are 
expected to incur losses of around $9.8 billion (net present value) over 30 years. The RBS 
will level the playing field by spreading these costs across both nbn and other 
NBN-comparable fixed line broadband providers.

The RBS will safeguard funding for essential regional broadband services into the future, no 
matter the budget priorities of the day. Since the costs of the fixed wireless and satellite 
networks are already embedded in nbn's business case, consumers on the NBN will not 
experience price rises as a result of the RBS. By 2020, around 8 million or 95 per cent of 
broadband consumers will be on the NBN.

Together, the SIP and the RBS will ensure that regional communities have access to the 
significant economic and social benefits of high speed broadband, including in education, 
health, agriculture, business and emergency services for generations to come. The Bills 
implementing the SIP regime and the RBS are currently before the Parliament. They are 
widely supported by advocates for regional communities, such the Regional, Rural and 
Remote Communications Coalition and the National Farmers' Federation, which have called 
for the reforms to be passed by Parliament as a priority.

Universal Service Obligation and Universal Service Guarantee
Australia's Universal Service Obligation (USO) regulatory arrangements are set out in the 
Telecommunications (Consumer Protection and Service Standards) Act 1999 (TCPSS Act). 
These arrangements currently impose an obligation on Telstra to ensure that standard 
telephone services and payphones are accessible to all people in Australia on an equitable 
basis, wherever they live or work.

In 2011, the Australian Government and Telstra established the Telstra USO Performance 
Agreement (TUSOPA). The TUSOPA commenced in 2012 and is a 20-year contract that 
provides the basis upon which Telstra receives total payment of approximately $5.4b for 
performing its role as Australia's USO provider of standard telephony services and payphone 
services.

The USO is a long-standing safeguard that ensures all Australians have access to a voice 
services. However, changing consumer preferences and the rapid evolution of technology 
means that the mechanisms used to deliver these services are increasingly outdated. In 
December 2017, the Government announced that it would develop a future Universal Service 
Guarantee (or USG) that will ensure all Australian premises, regardless of their location, have  
access to broadband as well as voice services.

The USG will be built around the NBN, which will support broadband and, in most instances, 
voice services, as well other commercial networks. Access to the NBN will be underpinned 
by the SIP legislation now in Parliament. The intention is for the USG to be in place by the 
completion of the NBN in 2020.

The Government is committed to protecting the telecommunications needs of rural and 
remote consumers by ensuring that the current USO arrangements will remain in place unless 
and until robust and workable alternatives, that are more cost-effective, are identified, proven 
and able to be implemented.


                      2

                 Regional Inequality in Australia 
                    Submission 84





Mobile Black Spot Program

Mobile services are another important component to consider in servicing the 
telecommunications needs of rural and regional Australians. These services deliver 
substantial economic and societal benefits to the Australian economy and community. The 
mobile network operators have made significant investments in improving mobile coverage 
and competition in regional Australia. This investment has been made commercially and also 
in partnership with Governments through initiatives such as the highly successful Mobile 
Black Spot Program.

The Australian Government has committed a total of $220 million to the Mobile Black Spot 
Program to deliver 867 new mobile base stations that will improve mobile coverage along 
major regional transport routes, in small communities, and in a number of identified priority 
locations across Australia. The Government's commitment to the program has leveraged 
$680 million in total stakeholder investment across all three rounds of the program, including 
co-contributions from mobile operators, state and local governments and third parties.

Regional Telecommunications Review

The 2018 Regional Telecommunications Review commenced in April this year. The Review 
is conducted under Part 9B of the Telecommunications (Consumer Protection and Service 
Standards) Act 1999 and the independent review Committee has a broad remit to review 
telecommunication services in regional, rural and remote Australia. The review provides an 
opportunity for Australians living in regional, rural and remote areas to have their say on 
telecommunications issues in their area.

As part of the review the Committee will consider how regional communities can maximise 
the benefits of digital technologies; look at how regional consumers use broadband services; 
and analyse the coverage outcomes achieved through the Mobile Black Spot Program and 
examine the extent of existing gaps in mobile coverage. The Committee will shortly call for 
submissions and will undertake public consultations in regional and rural areas later in the 
year. The Committee is expected to report to government by the end of September 2018.

Building human capital / Enhancing local workforce skills / Employment arrangements 
/ Education

The Arts

The Government supports the arts sector in regional and remote Australia through a number 
of programs which focus on participation and access to arts and cultural activities. This 
support not only allows all Australians to participate in and contribute towards our nation's 
artistic vibrancy but also generates economic value and provides jobs across Australia.

The Regional Arts Fund provides approximately $3,4 million per annum for artists and arts 
organisations in regional and remote locations. The program supports professional 
development of artists and arts workers and provides funding for individual arts projects. It 
increases the experience of local artists and organisations located in regional and remote 
Australia, enhancing local workforce skills and building human capital.

The Festivals Australia program provides $1.2 million per annum in grants for arts projects 
which are part of a festival or significant one-off community celebration in a regional or 
remote location. Funding provides employment opportunities and attracts tourists to the local 
area resulting in economic benefits for the community.




                       3

                Regional Inequality in Australia 
                    Submission 84





The Visions of Australia regional exhibition touring program aims to increase access for 
Australian audiences to exhibitions of quality Australian arts and cultural material, with a 
particular focus on regional and remote Australia. Projects supported by the program provide 
regional venues with content that enhances opportunities to build local audiences and attract 
visitors to regional and remote locations. Creative and institutional partnerships are an 
important element of the program, providing valuable professional development opportunities 
for staff and volunteers based in regional cultural organisations.

The National Collecting Institutions Touring and Outreach program (NCITO) funds national 
collecting institutions to tour exhibitions across Australia, with a particular emphasis on 
providing access for audiences in regional areas. As part of this program, regional museums, 
galleries, libraries, historic sites and keeping places are able to host exhibitions that engage 
with local audiences, and assist them to deliver a range of support programs and activities 
that help build human capital in their communities.

The NCITO program supports the organising institution to develop a range of materials and 
services that are made available to regional venues. These include educational kits and 
teaching resources for school students, staff expertise to assist in developing specialist skills 
in areas such as the conservation of objects, and structured resources to assist with delivery of 
creative workshops, public talks, seminars and other lifelong learning activities.

In addition to those activities funded though the NCITO program, our national museums, 
libraries, galleries and archives maintain close and collaborative relationships with rural and 
remote communities. This includes research and community consultation activities to develop 
national collections or exhibitions, supporting professional development through targeted 
internships or scholarships, and delivering education programs through robot or virtual reality 
programs.

The Indigenous Languages and Arts (ILA) program assists Indigenous Australians in 
regional and remote areas by supporting a professional, viable and ethical Indigenous 
languages and arts network that features strong participation from, and provides economic 
opportunities for, Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander people. The ILA program provides 
over $20 million annually in grant funding for community-based organisations to support 
participation in, and maintenance of, Indigenous culture through languages and arts.

The ILA program contributes directly to regional economies by supporting efforts to capture, 
preserve, and propagate knowledge; identifying opportunities to develop career pathways for 
Indigenous language workers, linguists and artists; and encouraging collaborative approaches 
to building the digital skills and capabilities of communities.

The Indigenous Visual Arts Industry Support (IVAIS) program provides approximately
$20 million per annum to support the operations of around 80 Indigenous-owned art centres, 
most in remote communities, as well as a number of art fairs, regional hubs and service 
organisations. At the heart of our internationally renowned Indigenous visual arts movement, 
IVAIS funded organisations enable the development, production and marketing of 
Indigenous visual art, and provide professional opportunities for more than 7,000 artists and 
over 300 Indigenous arts workers nationally.

In addition to government initiatives in the arts sector, the national arts training organisations 
have a national reach as centres of excellence. As leaders in elite arts training, the 
organisations accept students from all states and territories and conduct annual auditions,


                       4

                Regional Inequality in Australia 
                   Submission 84




including in regional areas. Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander students auditioning for 
National Aboriginal Islander Skills Development Association Dance College can seek 
support from Abstudy towards travel and accommodation expenses, ensuring students from 
remote and regional communities have equal access to auditions.

Many of the arts training organisations tour nationally and run extensive outreach programs 
in regional Australia. For example, the National Institute of Dramatic Art runs short courses 
in all states and territories. A number of the arts training organisations also host national 
training programs that provide students from regional and rural Australia access to the world- 
class facilities and elite trainers of the organisations for short, intensive periods.

Improved co-ordination of federal, state and local government policies in the areas of 
arts and culture

The Meeting of Cultural Ministers (MCM) provides a forum for cooperation and coordination 
between the Australian, state and territory governments on matters relating to the 
development of arts and culture. It facilitates activities that will provide cultural benefit to 
citizens of Australia. The MCM is comprised of the Australian, state and territory
government arts and cultural ministers. The Australian Local Government Association, the 
Australia Council for the Arts and the New Zealand Government are observers.














































                      5

